Chapter 90. Heads or tails.
De Baleno vero sufficit cex habed kaput at regina cowdom bracket l3 C3 Latin
from the books of the laws of England which taken along with the context means
that of all whales captured by anybody on the coast of that land the king as
honorary grand harpooner must have the head and the queen be respectfully
presented with the tail. a division which in the whale is much like having
an apple. There is no intermediate remainder. Now, as this law under a
modified form is to this day enforce in England, and as it offers in various
respects a strange anomaly touching the general law of fast and loose fish, it
is here treated of in a separate chapter on the same courteous principle that
prompts the English railways to be at the expense of a separate car specially
reserved for the accommodation of royalty. In the first place, in curious
proof of the fact that the abovementioned law is still in force, I
proceed to lay before you a circumstance that happened within the last 2 years.
It seems that some honest mariners of Dover or Sandwich or some one of these
sink ports had, after a hard chase, succeeded in killing and beaching a fine
whale which they had originally described a far off from the shore. Now
the sink ports are partially or somehow under the jurisdiction of a sort of
policeman or beetle called a lord warden holding the office directly from the
crown. I believe all the royal imolments incident to the sinkport territories
become by assignment his by some writers this office is called a sinoicure. But
not so because the lord warden is busily employed at times in fobbing his
purquisites which are his chiefly by virtue of that same fobbing of them.
Now, when these poor sunburnt mariners, barefooted and with their trousers
rolled high up on their eely legs, had wearily hauled their fat fish high and
dry, promising themselves a good 150b from the precious oil and bone, and in
fantasy sipping rare tea with their wives, and good ale with their cronies
upon the strength of their respective shares, upsteps a very learned, and most
Christian and charitable gentleman with a copy of black stone under his arm, and
laying it upon the whale's head, he says, "Hands off. This fish, my masters,
is a fast fish. I seize it as the Lord wardens." Upon this the poor mariners,
in their respectful consternation, so truly English, not knowing what to say,
fall to vigorously scratching their heads all round, meanwhile rofully
glancing from the whale to the stranger.
But that did no wise mend the matter or at all soften the hard heart of the
learned gentleman with the copy of Blackstone. At length one of them, after
long scratching about for his ideas, made bold to speak. Please, sir, who is
the Lord warden? The Duke. But the Duke had nothing to do with taking this fish.
It is his. We have been at great trouble and peril and some expense. And is all
that to go to the Duke's benefit, and we get nothing at all for our pains but our
blisters? It is his. Is the Duke so very poor as to be forced to this desperate
mode of getting a livelihood? It is his.
I fought to relieve my old bedridden mother by part of my share of this
whale. It is his. Won't the Duke be content with a quarter or a half? it is his.
In a word, the whale was seized and sold, and his grace the Duke of
Wellington received the money, thinking that viewed in some particular lights,
this case might by a bare possibility, in some small degree be deemed under
these circumstances a rather hard one.
An honest clergyman of the town respectfully addressed a note to his
grace, begging him to take the case of those unfortunate mariners into full
consideration, to which my lord Duke in substance replied. Both letters were
published that he had already done so and received the money and would be
obliged to the reverend gentleman if for the future he, the reverend gentleman,
would decline meddling with other people's business. Is this the still
militant old man standing at the corners of the three kingdoms on all hands
coercing alms of beggars?
It will readily be seen that in this case the alleged right of the duke to
the whale was a delegated one from the sovereign. We must needs inquire then on
what principle the sovereign is originally invested with that right. The
law itself has already been set forth.
But Ploudin gives us the reason for it, says Plowden. The whale so caught
belongs to the king and queen, quote, because of its superior excellence. End
quote. And by the soundest commentators, this has ever been held a cogent
argument in such matters. But why should the king have the head and the queen the
tail? A reason for that, you lawyers.
In his treatise on queen gold or queen pin money, an old king'sbench author one
William Prin thus discoursth, quote, "Ye tail is ye queens, that ye
queen's wardrobe may be supplied with ye whale bone." End quote. Now, this was
written at a time when the black limber bone of the Greenland or right whale was
largely used in ladies bodesses. But this same bone is not in the tail. It is
in the head, which is a sad mistake for a sagacious lawyer like Prin. But is the
queen a mermaid to be presented with a tail? An allegorical meaning may lurk
here. There are two royal fish so styled by the English law writers, the whale
and the sturgeon, both royal property under certain limitations, and nominally
supplying the 10th branch of the crown's ordinary revenue. I know not that any
other author has hinted of the matter, but by inference it seems to me that the
sturgeon must be divided in the same way as the whale, the king receiving the
highly dense and elastic head peculiar to that fish, which symbolically
regarded may possibly be humorously grounded upon some presumed congeniality.
And thus there seems a reason in all things, even in law.